<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://expath.org/ns/xmlspec/xmlspec.rnc"?>

<spec role="editors-copy" xmlns:ex="http://expath.org/ns/xmlspec" ex:w3c="true">
   <header>
      <title>HTTP Model</title>
      <w3c-designation>w3c-designation</w3c-designation>
      <w3c-doctype>EXPath Candidate Module</w3c-doctype>
      <pubdate>
         <day>11</day>
         <month>January</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pubdate>
      <publoc>
         <loc href="http://expath.org/spec/http/editor"/>
      </publoc>
      <altlocs>
         <loc href="http://expath.org/spec/http/editor.xml">XML</loc>
         <!--loc href="http://expath.org/spec/http/20120509/diff">Revision markup</loc-->
      </altlocs>
      <latestloc>
         <loc href="http://expath.org/spec/http"/>
      </latestloc>
      <!--prevlocs>
         <loc href="http://expath.org/spec/http/20101111"/>
      </prevlocs-->
      <authlist>
         <author role="editor">
            <name>Florent Georges</name>
            <affiliation><loc href="http://h2oconsulting.be/">H2O Consulting</loc></affiliation>
         </author>
      </authlist>
      <!--
          The copyright has to be adapted when this spec passes into "Final Report" status.
          See http://www.w3.org/community/reports/reqs/.
      -->
      <copyright>
         <p>Copyright © 2012-2014 Florent Georges, published by the <loc
               href="http://w3.org/community/expath/">EXPath Community Group</loc> under the <loc
               href="https://www.w3.org/community/about/agreements/cla/">W3C Community Contributor
               License Agreement (CLA)</loc>. A human-readable <loc
               href="http://www.w3.org/community/about/agreements/cla-deed/">summary</loc> is
            available.</p>
         <p>This specification was published by the <loc href="http://www.w3.org/community/expath/"
               >EXPath Community Group</loc>. It is not a W3C Standard nor is it on the W3C
            Standards Track. Please note that under the <loc
               href="http://www.w3.org/community/about/agreements/cla/">W3C Community Contributor
               License Agreement (CLA)</loc> there is a limited opt-out and other conditions apply.
            Learn more about <loc href="http://www.w3.org/community/">W3C Community and Business
               Groups</loc>.</p>
      </copyright>
      <abstract>
         <p>This module defines an XML format for HTTP requests and responses, as well as a set of
            functions to access specific informations of those requests and responses.</p>
      </abstract>
      <status>
         <p>Must be ignored, but is required by the schema...</p>
      </status>
      <langusage>
         <language>langusage</language>
      </langusage>
      <revisiondesc>
         <p>revisiondesc</p>
      </revisiondesc>
   </header>
   <body>
      <div1 id="ns">
         <head>Namespace conventions</head>
         <p>This module defines an XML format for HTTP requests and responses, as well as a set of
            functions to access specific informations of those requests and responses. Elements and
            functions defined by this module are in the namespace
               <code>http://expath.org/ns/http</code>. In this document, the <code>http</code>
            prefix, when used, is bound to this namespace URI.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="intro">
         <head>Introduction</head>
         <p>One of the obvious usages of XML if to transfer information between different systems,
            as a universally supported information representation language. In that regard, it is
            often used together with HTTP, as a universally supported transfert protocol. XPath and
            associated programming languages like XQuery and XSLT, are therefore often used to
            create or consume XML documents received or to be sent through HTTP. But they have no
            (standard) way to access or represent the information in the HTTP layer itself.</p>
         <p>This specification defines an XML format to represent HTTP requests and responses, which
            cary all the semantics of the HTTP layer. They are low-level formats aimed at mapping as
            closely as possible the HTTP specification, so all the power and expressiveness of HTTP
            is available to XPath. Libraries or other specifications can then use those requests and
            responses, to provide more high-level features on top of them. This specification does
            not define any way to send a request (as a client) or to receive a request and serve the
            corresponding response (as a server). Those features would have to be defined by other
            specifications or by specific products.</p>
         <p>Here is an example of HTTP request:</p>
         <eg><![CDATA[<http:request ...>
   ...
</http:request>]]></eg>
         <p>The corresponding response could look like:</p>
         <eg><![CDATA[<http:response ...>
   ...
</http:response>]]></eg>
         <p>Accessing the value of the header Content-Type in the response (given it is bound to the
            variable $response) could be done in XPath as following:</p>
         <eg>$response/http:header[@name eq 'content-type']/string(@value)</eg>
         <p>The exact same result can be achived by using the function http:header defined in this
            specification:</p>
         <eg>http:header($response, 'Content-Type')</eg>
         <p>This specification provides, in the appendices, the XML Schema for the XML format, as
            well as an XQuery library module and an XSLT stylesheet defining the functions as
            standard XQuery and XSLT functions. This is only informative, and an implementation can
            provide built-in functions as long as they provide the same results.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="randr">
         <head>Requests and responses</head>
         <p>TODO: Do we use the elements http:request and http:response, or like a single element
            http:entity? (with an attribute or element to tell whether they are or they are intended
            to be a request or a response) This allows to define functions for instance that accept
            either of them (like http:header() for instance). Other possibilities to solve this
            problem is to define a base type in XML Schema and use it in function signatures...</p>
         <p>The request and response are defined by the following elements:</p>
         <eg><![CDATA[<http:request
   method = method
   href = anyURI >
    (http:uri?,
     http:param*,
     http:header*,
     (http:body
      |http:multipart)?
</http:request>

<http:response
   code = code
   status = string? >
    (http:header*,
     (http:body
      |http:multipart)?
</http:response>]]></eg>
         <p>TODO: Is it possible to have query parameters in @href? It would be useful in the
            context of an HTTP client. In the context of a server-side container, it would be less a
            problem, as the user would mostly access the information, and we could provide different
            functions to access different "flavours" of the URI (with or without the query
            parameters, with or w/o the fragment identifier, etc.) The same is true for the element
            http:uri: it is useful mostly as a convenience to access the "parsed" URI, but this is
            not a big deal if we provide accessor functions (and we can provide as well a function
            to construct the full URI based on an element http:uri).</p>
         <p>TODO: Define that http:response/@status is optional in a server context (when the user
            constructs the response, so the implementation can set the standard status phrase for
            the given response code), but is mandatory in a client context (the implementation must
            then provide the user with the status phrase returned to the client). Same for
            http:request/http:uri, mandatory in a server context (but certainly not in a client
            context).</p>
         <p>The method name and the header names are always lower case. Because the case is not
            significant, it is then possible to the user to compare them (for instance to check the
            method or to select a specific header) by simple string comparison, instead of having to
            handle the case insensitivity (the corresponsing accessor functions provide the case
            insensitivity feature though).</p>
         <p>The element http:uri in the request is defined as follow:</p>
         <eg><![CDATA[<http:uri>
    (http:scheme,
     http:part,
     http:authority,
     (http:part,
      http:port)?,
     http:part*
</http:uri>]]></eg>
         <p>TODO: Include the query parameters and the fragment identifier as well?</p>
         <p>The element http:scheme is the HTTP scheme, either http or https. The element authority
            is the machine name, either an IP address or a domain name. The element port is,
            unsurprisingly, the port number, as an integer. The elements http:part contain any other
            text part of the URI, as a string. The first one has always the value "://". The one
            before the port, if any, has always the value ":". The following elements http:part can
            present the URI split in any number of pieces, as defined by the implementation. The
            rule is that concatenating the value of all the elements in the document order
            reconstruct the same URI as in http:request/@href. The element http:part is defined
            as:</p>
         <eg><![CDATA[<http:part
   name = token? >
    text
</http:part>]]></eg>
         <p>In particular, note the optional attribute @name. A server-side implementation can
            provide a way to "parse" the request URI, for instance for RESTfull services, and break
            it down to pieces, annotating some of them with names. The following URI for
            instance:</p>
         <eg>http://example.org/users/fgeorges</eg>
         <p>could result in the following element http:uri:</p>
         <eg><![CDATA[<http:uri>
   <http:scheme>http</http:scheme>
   <http:part>://</http:part>
   <http:authority>example.org</http:authority>
   <http:part>/users/</http:part>
   <http:part name="id">fgeorges</http:part>
</http:uri>]]></eg>
         <p>The way names are attributed is implementation-defined. With the above http:uri element,
            the user can then easily retrieve the ID of the user from the URI with:</p>
         <eg>$request/http:uri/http:part[@name eq 'id']/string(.)</eg>
         <p>Note: Informally, the intend is to provide server context libraries, framworks and
            specifications the ability to "parse" the URI and name some specific parts. This is
            useful in RESTful environment for instance, like the above example suggests. If a
            RESTful specification defines a way to map requests to implementations based on URI path
            patterns, the above example could be generated by the following pattern (on example.org
            then): "/users/{id}".</p>
         <p>The elements http:param and http:header are defined as follow:</p>
         <eg><![CDATA[<http:param
   name = token? >
    text
</http:param>

<http:header
   name = token? >
    text
</http:header>]]></eg>
         <p>The elements http:body and http:multipart are defined as follow:</p>
         <eg><![CDATA[<http:multipart
   content-type = string
   separator = string? >
    (http:header*,
     http:body)+
</http:multipart>

<http:body
   content-type = string
   position = integer? >
    (text
     |document-node)?
</http:body>]]></eg>
         <p>The attribute content-type is the content of the multipart or single body. The attribute
            position is used on the body elements when they are children of a multipart entity. The
            attribute separator is the multipart separator string (it is optional so when it is used
            on a response in a server-side context, or on a request in a client context, the
            implementation can compute it automatically; it must be present on a request in a
            server-side context and on a response in a client-side context).</p>
         <p>The content of a body element is optional. Besides the fact that the content of a body
            can be empty, this is also a way to let a specific library or specification to define a
            way to pass the content of a body alongside the HTTP element, instead of embedding it
            (this is outside the scope of this specification). For instance, an HTTP client could
            accept an HTTP request element and a sequence of items representing the content of the
            bodies (or it could require the content to be embedded in the http:body elements all the
            time).</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="functions">
         <head>Functions</head>
         <p>Most of the functions defined in this specification are convenience functions to access
            specific information from the request and response elements. They take such a request or
            a response as parameter (except <xtermref href="#f.request">http:request</xtermref>),
            and a such could be written as standard user functions in XQuery or XSLT. Defining those
            functions in this specification achieves 3 different goals: 1) providing the user with
            those functions even in XPath, which does not allow defining user functions, 2)
            providing the user with those functions without requiring to write them over and over
            again, in XQuery and XSLT, or to have to import libraries, and 3) providing the
            implementation with optimization opportunities.</p>
         <p>The function <xtermref href="#f.request">http:request</xtermref> is different in this
            regards, as it does not return inormation from a request or a response, but it returns
            the "<emph>current in-scope request</emph>". All other functions are functional, in the
            sense that they return some values based on their parameters (the returned values depend
            only on the parameters, and are always the same for the same parameters). But the
            function <xtermref href="#f.request">http:request</xtermref> does not take any
            parameter, it depends on the dynamic context when it is called, and so makes the
            function it is called from not functional.</p>
         <p>The use of the function <xtermref href="#f.request">http:request</xtermref> is
            deprecated as much as possible. In a server-side environment, the specification or the
            product defining the HTTP layer should provide a way to pass the HTTP request to the
            user code, e.g. through a stylesheet or a query parameter.</p>
         <p>The other functions take an HTTP entity as first parameter. Some functions expect a
            request, some expect a response, and others expect any of them.</p>
         <note>
            <p>TODO: Describe the advantages and drawbacks of having 2 different names for
                  <code>http:request</code> and <code>http:response</code> (probably deriving from
               the same common XML Schema base type), versus having one element
                  <code>http:entity</code> with an attribute telling whether it is a request or a
               response.</p>
         </note>
         <div2 id="f.header">
            <head>http:header</head>
            <eg>
<ex:function>http:header</ex:function>($entity as element(*, http:entity),
            $name   as xs:string) as xs:string*
</eg>
            <p>This function returns the values of the headers with the name $name in the HTTP
               entity $entity. A header can appear several times in HTTP, so the return value is a
               sequence of string. If the header does not appear in the entity, the empty sequence
               is returned.</p>
            <p>The names of the headers are case-insensitive. The following calls therefore all
               return the same values:</p>
            <eg>http:header($response, 'Content-Type')
http:header($response, 'content-type')
http:header($response, 'CoNtEnT-tYpE')</eg>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="f.header-names">
            <head>http:header-names</head>
            <eg>
<ex:function>http:header-names</ex:function>($entity as element(*, http:entity)) as xs:string*
</eg>
            <p>This function returns the name of all the headers in the $entity. If a header appears
               more than once, its name is returned only once. The order of the names is undefined,
               but is stable accros several calls on the same element.</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="f.param">
            <head>http:param</head>
            <eg>
<ex:function>http:param</ex:function>($entity as element(*, http:entity),
           $name   as xs:string) as xs:string*
</eg>
            <p>This function returns the values of the parameters with the name $name in the HTTP
               entity $entity. If the parameter does not appear in the entity, the empty sequence is
               returned. A parameter is either a query parameter from the URI, or a parameter from
               the body (TODO: define exactly under which conditions, which match the HTML
               specification, like x-www-url-encoded-parameters, are something like that).</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="f.param-names">
            <head>http:param-names</head>
            <eg>
<ex:function>http:param-names</ex:function>($entity as element(*, http:entity)) as xs:string*
</eg>
            <p>This function returns the name of all the parameters in the $entity. Parameters are
               defined in the definition of the function http:param. The order of the names is
               undefined, but is stable accros several calls on the same element.</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="f.is-request">
            <head>http:is-request</head>
            <eg>
<ex:function>http:is-request</ex:function>($entity as element(*, http:entity)) as boolean
</eg>
            <p>This function returns true if $entity is an HTTP request, false if it is a
               response.</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="f.is-response">
            <head>http:is-response</head>
            <eg>
<ex:function>http:is-response</ex:function>($entity as element(*, http:entity)) as boolean
</eg>
            <p>This function returns true if $entity is an HTTP response, false if it is a
               request.</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="f.method">
            <head>http:method</head>
            <eg>
<ex:function>http:method</ex:function>($request as element(http:request)) as xs:string
</eg>
            <p>This function returns the method of $request. The method name is always in lower
               case.</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="f.href">
            <head>http:href</head>
            <eg>
<ex:function>http:href</ex:function>($request as element(http:request)) as xs:string?
</eg>
            <p>This function returns the href of $request.</p>
            <p>TODO: Define what it contains (fragment identifier?, query parameters?, etc.)</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="f.scheme">
            <head>http:scheme</head>
            <eg>
<ex:function>http:scheme</ex:function>($request as element(http:request)) as xs:string?
</eg>
            <p>This function returns the URI scheme of $request. The scheme is either 'http' ot
               'https'.</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="f.authority">
            <head>http:authority</head>
            <eg>
<ex:function>http:authority</ex:function>($request as element(http:request)) as xs:string?
</eg>
            <p>This function returns the URI scheme of $request.</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="f.port">
            <head>http:port</head>
            <eg>
<ex:function>http:port</ex:function>($request as element(http:request)) as xs:integer
</eg>
            <p>This function returns the port number of $request. This is the actual port a request
               has to be sent to (in a client context) or has been received on (in a server
               context), regardless whether is has been explicitely written or not in the request
               URI.</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="f.uri-part">
            <head>http:uri-part</head>
            <eg>
<ex:function>http:uri-part</ex:function>($request as element(http:request),
              $name    as xs:string) as xs:string?
</eg>
            <p>This function returns the value of the URI part with the same name as $name. The name
               comparison is using the codepoint collation. The way some parts are named is
               implementation-defined (see also the definition of [http:uri]).</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="f.code">
            <head>http:code</head>
            <eg>
<ex:function>http:code</ex:function>($response as element(http:response)) as xs:integer
</eg>
            <p>This function returns the result code of $response. For instance 200 for a succesful
               response, or 404 for a "Page not found" error.</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="f.status">
            <head>http:status</head>
            <eg>
<ex:function>http:status</ex:function>($response as element(http:response)) as xs:string
</eg>
            <p>This function returns the status line of $response. In a server context, if $response
               has not been given an explicit status line, then this function returns the default
               value the implementation will use, given $response status code (as defined in the
               HTTP specification, e.g. "OK" for 200 or "Page not found" for 404).</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="f.bodies">
            <head>http:bodies</head>
            <eg>
<ex:function>http:bodies</ex:function>($entity as element(*, http:entity)) as element(http:body)*
</eg>
            <p>This function returns the body descriptors of $entity. There is one optional body
               descriptor (that is one element http:body) for single part requests and responses,
               but there can be several body descriptors in case of multipart requests or responses
               (one of them for each part in the multipart entity).</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="f.body">
            <head>http:body</head>
            <eg>
<ex:function>http:body</ex:function>($entity as element(*, http:entity)) as element(http:body)?
<ex:function>http:body</ex:function>($entity as element(*, http:entity),
          $pos    as xs:integer) as element(http:body)?
</eg>
            <p>This function returns a specific body descriptor of $entity. The first arity can be
               used only for single part requests and responses. It throws the error
               http:not-a-single-part if $entity has a multipart content type. The second arity
               returns the body descriptor at position $pos, in case of multipart (the position
               numbering starts at 1). If $pos is 1 and $entity is a single part content type, it
               return the same results as the first arity. If $pos is greater than 1 and $entity has
               a single part content type, it throws the error http:not-multipart. Both arities
               throw the error http:out-of-bound if $pos is lower than 1. If there is no body
               corresponding to position $pos (or if the single part has no body for the first
               arity), the empty sequence is returned.</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="f.get-body">
            <head>http:get-body</head>
            <eg>
<ex:function>http:get-body</ex:function>($body as element(http:body)) as item()
<ex:function>http:get-body</ex:function>($body   as element(http:body),
              $bodies as item()*) as item()
</eg>
            <p>This function returns the actual content associated with a body descriptor. The first
               arity get the content from the body descriptor only, whilst the second arity can use
               the body content list passed as $bodies. In some cases, a server context
               implementation can provide the user code with an http:request and a body content
               list, so the body content can be lazy evaluated more easily, without being embedded
               in http:request. More fundamentally, if the body content is XML, we really want a
               separate XML document node to be returned, instead of an element node, child of the
               http:body (traversing the parent or ancestor axis would then be surprising, by
               returning the http:body or http:request, which is really not what we want from a body
               content.</p>
            <p>TODO: Should we define more precisely the body content list? Should we use a map?
               Should we then impose such a separate list? (which makes a lot of sense for XML
               document bodies, to avoid them to be poluted by their http:body parent, like in SOAP
               envelopes). But then, it would make sense to make the map itself representing the
               whole request or response, and so to make it the parameter of most functions here. So
               it would be not possible to implement it without map support... Which really is a an
               acceptable strategy (isn't it what the Binary Module is doing?)</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="f.id">
            <head>http:id</head>
            <eg>
<ex:function>http:id</ex:function>($entity as element(*, http:entity)) as xs:string
</eg>
            <p>This function returns a string which is unique to $entity. The context of uniqueness
               is implementation-defined, but is losely defined to be a single web server or client,
               not restricted to one XPath, XQuery or XSLT evaluation.</p>
            <note>
               <p>Note: For instance, on a server, this can be used to log each request received in
                  a separate file, as the returned ID will be different for all
                     <code>http:request</code> elements, but always the same for the same request.
                  This is guaranteed by the implementation even between different evaluations.</p>
            </note>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="f.request">
            <head>http:request</head>
            <eg>
<ex:function>http:request</ex:function>() as element(http:request)
</eg>
            <p>This function returns the HTTP request from the context, in a server context.</p>
            <p>It is the only function in this specification depending on the context, all other
               functions get an explicit HTTP request or response as parameter. An implementation
               might chose not to support it (in which case it throws an error http:not-supported).
               If an implementation chose to support this function, it is encouraged to provide the
               user with the ability to enable or disable this support (e.g. through some
               implementation-defined configuration machanism). A server context library, framework
               or specification using this module is then encouraged to define another way to pass
               the HTTP request to the user code (e.g. through external parameters for an XQuery
               main module), so the user always have a way not to use this function. If only for
               that, it is better and easier to test to write code not using the execution
               context.</p>
            <p>...</p>
         </div2>
      </div1>
   </body>
</spec>
