<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://expath.org/ns/xmlspec/xmlspec.rnc" type="compact"?>

<spec role="editors-copy" xmlns:ex="http://expath.org/ns/xmlspec" ex:w3c="true">
   <header>
      <title>Web Applications</title>
      <w3c-designation>w3c-designation</w3c-designation>
      <w3c-doctype>EXPath Candidate Module</w3c-doctype>
      <pubdate>
         <day>1</day>
         <month>April</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pubdate>
      <publoc>
         <loc href="http://expath.org/spec/webapp/20130401"/>
      </publoc>
      <altlocs>
         <loc href="http://expath.org/spec/webapp/20130401.xml">XML</loc>
      </altlocs>
      <latestloc>
         <loc href="http://expath.org/spec/webapp"/>
      </latestloc>
      <!--prevlocs>
         <loc href="http://expath.org/spec/webapp/20130401"/>
      </prevlocs-->
      <authlist>
         <author role="editor">
            <name>Florent Georges</name>
            <affiliation><loc href="http://h2oconsulting.be/">H2O Consulting</loc></affiliation>
         </author>
      </authlist>
      <!--
          The copyright has to be adapted when this spec passes into "Final Report" status.
          See http://www.w3.org/community/reports/reqs/.
      -->
      <copyright>
         <p>Copyright © 2011-2013 Florent Georges, published by the <loc
               href="http://w3.org/community/expath/">EXPath Community Group</loc> under the <loc
               href="https://www.w3.org/community/about/agreements/cla/">W3C Community Contributor
               License Agreement (CLA)</loc>. A human-readable <loc
               href="http://www.w3.org/community/about/agreements/cla-deed/">summary</loc> is
            available.</p>
         <p>This specification was published by the <loc href="http://www.w3.org/community/expath/"
               >EXPath Community Group</loc>. It is not a W3C Standard nor is it on the W3C
            Standards Track. Please note that under the <loc
               href="http://www.w3.org/community/about/agreements/cla/">W3C Community Contributor
               License Agreement (CLA)</loc> there is a limited opt-out and other conditions apply.
            Learn more about <loc href="http://www.w3.org/community/">W3C Community and Business
               Groups</loc>.</p>
      </copyright>
      <abstract>
         <p>This specification defines how to write web applications on server-side, using XML
            technologies like XSLT, XQuery and XProc. It also defines their execution context, as
            well as some functions they can use. Last but not least it defines how to package such
            webapps, by using the <bibref ref="pkg"/>.</p>
      </abstract>
      <status>
         <p>Must be ignored, but is required by the schema...</p>
      </status>
      <langusage>
         <language>langusage</language>
      </langusage>
      <revisiondesc>
         <p>revisiondesc</p>
      </revisiondesc>
   </header>
   <body>
      <div1 id="intro">
         <head>Introduction</head>
         <div2 id="namespaces">
            <head>Namespace conventions</head>
            <p>The webapp descriptor uses the namespace <code>http://expath.org/ns/webapp</code>, as
               the default namespace. This namespace is also used for the XML representation of the
               HTTP requests and responses, and to define several functions provided by the webapp
               container. In this document, the <code>web</code> prefix, when used, is bound to this
               namespace URI.</p>
            <p>Error codes are defined in the namespace <code>http://expath.org/ns/error</code>. In
               this document, the <code>err</code> prefix, when used, is bound to this namespace
               URI.</p>
         </div2>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="containers">
         <head>Containers and webapps</head>
         <p>A web application, or webapp, in this specification, is a set of components,
            implementing an application. The application responds to HTTP requests and runs in a
            webapp container. The container provides the context of execution for the webapps,
            provides them with some functions, and is responsible for translating from and to HTTP.
            When the container receives an HTTP request, it identifies the corresponding component
            to process it (e.g. based on the request URL), builds an XML representation of the
            request, and call the component. The component receives the HTTP request as an XML
            document, and returns an XML description of the HTTP response to send back to the
            client. The container then translates this XML document and actually send the
            corresponding HTTP response.</p>
         <p>A component is a piece of XSLT, XQuery or XProc. Each type of component defines how the
            request is passed to and the response is returned by such a component. But the XML
            format of the requests and responses is always the same. The existing types of
            components are:</p>
         <ulist>
            <item><p>an XSLT stylesheet</p></item>
            <item><p>an XSLT function</p></item>
            <item><p>an XSLT template</p></item>
            <item><p>an XQuery query</p></item>
            <item><p>an XQuery function</p></item>
            <item><p>an XProc pipeline</p></item>
            <item><p>an XProc step</p></item>
         </ulist>
         <p>A webapp contains a descriptor, which defines how to dispatch a request to a specific
            component. The dispatching mechanism is based on the request URL, by associating a URL
            pattern to a component public URI (a component public URI is defined in the <bibref
               ref="pkg"/>, basically it is the component name, as an absolute URI). The association
            of a URL pattern to a component is called a servlet. Every servlet has a name.</p>
         <p>A webapp is installed at a specific context root. The context root is a path prefix, and
            all the request received "below" that prefix are served by that webapp. For instance, a
            webapp installed on example.org at the context root /somewhere will serve all requests
            with a URL starting with <code>http://example.org/somewhere/</code>. The part after that
            prefix is the path to the servlet.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="req-resp">
         <head>Requests and responses</head>
         <p>The HTTP requests and responses are represented as XML documents. The request is build
            by the container to represent the actual HTTP request received. The component returns a
            representation of the response, used by the container to actually respond to the client
            over HTTP. A sample request:</p>
         <eg>
&lt;request servlet="some" path="/some/resource" method="get" xmlns="http://expath.org/ns/webapp">
   &lt;url>http://example.org/myapp/some/resource&lt;/url>
   &lt;authority>http://example.org&lt;/authority>
   &lt;context-root>/myapp&lt;/context-root>
   &lt;path>
      &lt;part>/some/&lt;/part>
      &lt;match name="rsrc">resource&lt;/match>
   &lt;/path>
   &lt;header name="host" value="example.org"/>
   &lt;header name="user-agent" value="Firefox/7.0.1"/>
   &lt;header name="accept" value="text/html,application/xml;q=0.9,*/*;q=0.8"/>
   &lt;header name="accept-language" value="en-us,en;q=0.5"/>
&lt;/request>
</eg>
         <p>This request can be build by a container listening at http://example.org/, when received
            a request to GET the resource at /myapp/some/resource. We can see the path has been
            pre-analyzed, and the request contains various HTTP information like the method, the
            request URL (decomposed in different ways), and the headers. The request might also
            contain an entity content, also known as the body of the request (e.g. in case of a PUT
            request).</p>
         <p>In response to the above request, the invoked component could return the following
            response to the container:</p>
         <eg>
&lt;response status="200" message="Ok" xmlns="http://expath.org/ns/webapp">
   &lt;header name="X-My-Header" value="Just an example."/>
   &lt;body content-type="application/xml">
      &lt;hello>World!&lt;/hello>
   &lt;/body>
&lt;/response>
</eg>
         <p>This tells the container to return the XML document
               <code>&lt;hello>World!&lt;/hello></code> to the client, using the Content-Type
            "application/xml", with the HTTP status code 200, and an extra header.</p>
         <div2 id="requests">
            <head>Requests</head>
            <p>A HTTP requet is represented by a sequence, the <emph>request sequence</emph>. The
               first item in that sequence is an element <code>web:request</code>, remaining items
               representing the entity content (there might be several of them in case of
               multipart). The web:request element is defined as the following:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;request servlet = NCName
         path = string
         method = NCName>
   url,
   authority,
   context-root,
   path,
   param*,
   header*,
   (body|
    multipart)?
&lt;/request>
</eg>
            <p>A request contains the name of the matched <code>servlet</code>, the request
                  <code>path</code>, and its <code>method</code> (also known as the HTTP verb, like
               GET and POST) in lower case. The text element <code>url</code> contains the original
               request URL, including its query parameters if any. The URL also appears cut down
               into several pieces. The element <code>authority</code> is its first part, including
               the URL scheme and the domain name, <code>context-root</code> is the webapp context
               root, <code>path</code> is an alternative representation of the requested path (as in
               the attribute <code>path</code>), where some specific parts have been analyzed, and
               the elements <code>param</code> represent the query parameters.</p>
            <p>Then come the HTTP <code>header</code> elements, each with a name and a value. Then
               the content of the HTTP entity (e.g. for a PUT), as an element <code>body</code> or
                  <code>multipart</code>, depending on the content type of the request.</p>
            <eg>
&lt;header name = string
        value = string>
   <emph>empty</emph>
&lt;header>
</eg>
            <p><kw>URL</kw></p>
            <p>The URL appears at several places in the request element, under different shapes. The
               element <code>url</code> is the original URL as typed by the user. Or at least it is
               an educated guess of what it could be, as HTTP does not include the original URL in
               the request (the port number for instance is not in the HTTP request).</p>
            <p>The element <code>authority</code> is the first part of the URL, including the URL
               scheme and the domain name (up to the slash first, but not including it). The scheme
               can be either "http:" or "https:". It is then followed by two slashes then the domain
               name.</p>
            <p>The element <code>context-root</code> is the webapp context root on this server. It
               is fixed for the webpp, and represents where the webapp has been "installed" on the
               server (the webapp serves all requests coming to URLs "below" its context root).</p>
            <p>After the element <code>path</code> (see below), the query parameters, if any, are
               represented each with an element <code>param</code>, with an attribute
                  <code>name</code> and an attribute <code>value</code>.</p>
            <eg>
&lt;param name = string
       value = string>
   <emph>empty</emph>
&lt;param>
</eg>
            <p>Note that the XPath expression "<code>fn:concat(authority, context-root,
               path)</code>" gives the original URL except the query parameters.</p>
            <p><kw id="path">Path</kw></p>
            <p>The path is the part of the request URL that comes after the context root (excluding
               the query parameters). This is thus the part that can vary for a given webapp (for a
               given webapp, deployed on a specific server at a specific context root, everything up
               to and including the context root will be always the same). Servlets use regexes to
               match URLs, and they can give a name to some sub parts of the path matched by the
               regex (see the definition of the webapp descriptor for all details).</p>
            <p>This is represented by having, in the element <code>path</code>, a sequence of
               elements <code>part</code> and <code>match</code>. The elements <code>part</code> are
               the non-matched parts of the URL, and the elements <code>match</code> are the matched
               parts of the URL. They appear in the same order as in the URL.</p>
            <eg>
&lt;path>
   (part|
    match)+
&lt;/path>

&lt;part>
   <emph>string</emph>
&lt;/part>

&lt;match name = NCName>
   <emph>string</emph>
&lt;/part>
</eg>
            <p>The entire path is the string value of the element <code>path</code>. Put another
               way, concatenating all the <code>part</code> and <code>match</code> elements, in
               order, gives the value of the path. It is also available as the value of the
               attribute <code>path</code> on the element <code>request</code>. See <specref
               ref="servlets"/> for an example.</p>
            <p><kw>Content</kw></p>
            <p>The body of the request, in HTTP parlance the entity content, is not embedded in the
               XML element representing the request (that is the web:request element). It is instead
               represented as a standalone item in the sequence representing the request. There
               might be several items in case of multipart. Each item can be of one of the following
               types:</p>
            <ulist>
               <item><p>a document node in case of an XML or HTML media type</p></item>
               <item><p>an xs:string in case of an textual media type</p></item>
               <item><p>an xs:base64Binary in case of any other media type</p></item>
            </ulist>
            <p>Selecting the media part is done based on the Content-Type header. In case of a
               multipart type, each part is represented by its own item. Each part's pseudo header
               Content-Type is used the same way that the header Content-Type is used for the entire
               content in case of a single part. The content type is used as follows:</p>
            <ulist>
               <item>
                  <p>An XML media type has a MIME type of <code>text/xml</code>,
                     <code>application/xml</code>, <code>text/xml-external-parsed-entity</code>, or
                     <code>application/xml-external-parsed-entity</code>, as defined in <bibref
                     ref="rfc3023"/> (except that <code>application/xml-dtd</code> is considered a
                     text media type). MIME types ending by <code>+xml</code> are also XML media
                     types.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>An HTML media type has a MIME type of <code>text/html</code>. The precise
                     algorithm to parse HTML into an XDM document node is
                     implementation-defined.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Text media types are the remaining types beginning with <code>text/</code>.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Binary types are all the other types. An implementation can treat some of those
                     binary types as either an XML, HTML or text media type if it is more
                     appropriate (this is implementation-defined).</p>
               </item>
            </ulist>
            <p>If the content type is <code>text/html</code>, the content is parsed into an XDM
               document node (using some HTML parsing algorithm that is out of the scope of this
               specification). If the content type is <code>application/xml</code>, or
               <code>text/xml</code>, or ends with <code>+xml</code>, </p>
            <p>The content itself is represented as additional items in the request sequence, but
               for each part, there is a <code>web:body</code> element in the
               <code>web:request</code> element, describing the part. In case of multipart, the
               <code>web:body</code> elements are wrapped into a <code>web:multipart</code> element.
               In case of no mutipart, there is one <code>web:body</code> element, direct child of
               <code>web:request</code>:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;multipart>
   (header*,
    body)+
&lt;/multipart>

&lt;header body = integer
        name = string
        value = string>
   <emph>empty</emph>
&lt;header>

&lt;body position = integer
      content-type = string>
   <emph>empty</emph>
&lt;body>
</eg>
            <p>The attribute <code>position</code> is the position of the body in a multipart (1, 2,
               3...) In case if a single part, it is always 1. The pseudo headers for each part in a
               multipart are before the part they relate to. Their attribute <code>body</code> also
               contains the corresponding body position. It is therefore possible to use either
               positional grouping (all the consecutive <code>web:header</code> elements right
               before a <code>web:body</code> element relates to this one), or value-based grouping
               (the <code>web:header</code> elements relate to the <code>web:body</code> element
               with the same position number). The body position number is also the position of the
               corresponding content in the request sequence (the <code>web:request</code> element
               is the first item, then comes the body #1, then the body #2, and so on).</p>
            <p>Note that the <code>web:header</code> elements that are children of a
               <code>web:multipart</code> have the same structure as when they are children of
               <code>web:request</code>, except they have the extra attribute <code>body</code>.</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="responses">
            <head>Responses</head>
            <p>When invoked, the top-level component (or group, or filter, if any) must return a
               sequence, the <emph>response sequence</emph>. The first item must be an element
               <code>web:response</code>, the remaining items being the content of the response to
               sent back to the client.</p>
            <eg>
&lt;response status = integer
          message = string>
   header*,
   (body|
    multipart)?
&lt;/response>
</eg>
            <p>The attribute <code>status</code> is the HTTP status code, and the attribute
               <code>message</code> is the HTTP status message. The elements <code>web:header</code>
               represent HTTP header to set in the response, and look like the same elements in the
               request.</p>
            <eg>
&lt;multipart>
   (header*,
    body)+
&lt;/multipart>

&lt;body item-position = integer?
      src = uri?
      charset = string?
      content-type = string>
   <emph>optional content</emph>
&lt;/body>
</eg>
            <p>The elements <code>web:multipart</code> and <code>web:body</code> represent the
               content to send back to the client, in a similar way as they are represented by the
               container in the request. The difference is that the pseudo-headers do not have an
               attribute <code>body</code>, the elements <code>web:body</code> do noy have an
               attribute <code>position</code>, and they might have an attribute <code>src</code>,
               an attribute <code>charset</code> and an attribute <code>item-position</code>, and
               they might have content. The content, <code>src</code> and <code>item-position</code>
               are mutually exclusive. If none of them is present, the body is empty.
               <code>charset</code> is the character encoding, for non-binary media types, and is
               UTF-8 by default. <code>item-position</code> is the position within the response
               sequence of the item representing the content of the correpsonding part, after the
               <code>web:response</code> element (that is, the first item after the response
               element, which is the second item in the sequence, has the position 1, the next one
               the position 2, and so on). <code>src</code> is the location of a file to return (it
               is resolve against the base URI of the <code>web:body</code> element).</p>
            <p>For instance, the following example, when returned as the evaluation of a component
               (either a servlet, or the top-level filter if there is any), will return a <code>200
               - Ok</code> to the client, with the header <code>Content-Disposition: file;
               filename="archive.zip"</code>, and the content is the file <code>archive.zip</code>,
               resolved next to the stylesheet that generated the response element (let us say it
               has been generated by an XSLT stylesheet that kept the default base URI of the
               stylesheet itself, so the file is part of the webapp package itself):</p>
            <eg>
&lt;response status="200" message="Ok">
   &lt;header name="Content-Disposition" value="file; filename=&amp;quot;archive.zip&amp;quot;"/>
   &lt;body content-type="application/zip" src="archive.zip"/>
&lt;/response>
</eg>
         </div2>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="components">
         <head>Components</head>
         <p>A component is a piece of code, written in one of the supported languages, that is
            executed in some specific context. For instance in response to a HTTP request, or as the
            action associated to a filter. A component must follow a few rules (for instance the
            number or name of parameters), so the web container can call it. A component is declared
            in the webapp descriptor. The format of the webapp descriptor is defined in the section
            <specref ref="descriptor"/>, but the corresponding config for each single type of
            component is described here in more detail.</p>
         <p>The webapp itsef is packaged as a standard EXPath package (see <bibref ref="pkg"/>).
            Each component must be identifiable through the package descriptor (e.g. an XSLT
            stylesheet must have a public import URI condigured in the package, or the namespace of
            the XQuery library module containing the function used as a component must be declared
            in the package as well).</p>
         <div2 id="xproc">
            <head>XProc</head>
            <p>An XProc component can be a pipeline, identified by its public import URI:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;xproc uri="http://example.org/ns/my-webapp/pipeline.xproc"/>
</eg>
            <p>An XProc component can also be a step type, identified by its QName:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;xproc uri="http://example.org/ns/my-webapp/step-library.xproc"
       step="app:my-step"/>
</eg>
            <p>The prefix used in the <code>step</code> attribute must be declared in scope (in the
               example above, the prefix <code>app</code> must be bound to the namespace of the
               step).</p>
            <p>Both pipelines and steps must have one input port named <code>source</code>, which
               accepts a sequence of documents, and one output port named <code>result</code>, which
               might return a sequence of documents. When used as an error handler, they must have
               an input port called <code>user-data</code>, which must accepts a sequence of
               documents (only of the application use the user data feature of error reporting, to
               pass any data from where the error is thrown to the error handler, see <specref
               ref="error-handling"/> for details).</p>
            <p>The following is a simple example of a pipeline, returning the XML representation of
               the HTTP request as the response itself:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;p:declare-step xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc"
                xmlns:web="http://expath.org/ns/webapp"
                xmlns:app="http://example.org/ns/my-webapp"
                xmlns:pkg="http://expath.org/ns/pkg"
                pkg:import-uri="http://example.org/my-webapp/echo.xproc"
                name="main"
                version="1.0">

   &lt;p:input  port="source" primary="true" sequence="true"/>
   &lt;p:output port="result" primary="true" sequence="true">
      &lt;p:pipe step="response" port="result"/>
      &lt;p:pipe step="main"     port="source"/>
   &lt;/p:output>

   &lt;!--
      Echoes the web:request element, ignores the bodies if any.
   -->

   &lt;p:identity name="response">
      &lt;p:input port="source">
         &lt;p:inline>
            &lt;web:response status="200" message="Ok">
               &lt;web:body content-type="application/xml"/>
            &lt;/web:response>
         &lt;/p:inline>
      &lt;/p:input>
   &lt;/p:identity>

&lt;/p:declare-step>
</eg>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="xquery">
            <head>XQuery</head>
            <p>An XQuery component can be a main module (also called a "query"), identified by its
               public import URI:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;xquery uri="http://example.org/ns/my-webapp/query.xq"/>
</eg>
            <p>An XQuery component can also be a function, identified by its QName:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;xquery function="app:my-function"/>
</eg>
            <p>The prefix used in the <code>function</code> attribute must be declared in scope (in
               the example above, the prefix <code>app</code> must be bound to the namespace of the
               function). Because the XQuery library modules are identified by their target
               namespace in the package descriptor, the name of the function itself is enough to
               identify uniquely the function.</p>
            <p>The request sequence (containing the <code>web:request</code> element and the request
               bodies) is passed to the XQuery function through its only parameter, and to the
               XQuery module through the external variable named <code>$web:input</code> (the
               <code>web:request</code> element is also set as the context element for evaluating
               the query).</p>
            <p>The following is a simple example of a function, returning the XML representation of
               the HTTP request as the response itself:</p>
            <eg>
xquery version "1.0";

module namespace app = "http://example.org/ns/my-webapp";

(:~
 : Echoes the web:request element, ignores the bodies if any.
 :)
declare function app:echo($input as item()+) as element()+
{ 
   &lt;web:response status="200" message="Ok">
      &lt;web:body content-type="application/xml"/>
   &lt;/web:response>
   ,
   $input[1]
};
</eg>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="xslt">
            <head>XSLT</head>
            <p>An XSLT component can be a stylesheet, identified by its public import URI:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;xslt uri="http://example.org/ns/my-webapp/stylesheet.xsl"/>
</eg>
            <p>An XSLT component can also be a named template, identified by its QName:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;xslt uri="http://example.org/ns/my-webapp/stylesheet.xsl"
      template="app:my-template"/>
</eg>
            <p>An XSLT component can also be a function, identified by its QName:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;xslt uri="http://example.org/ns/my-webapp/stylesheet.xsl"
      function="app:my-function"/>
</eg>
            <p>The prefix used in both the <code>function</code> and <code>template</code>
               attributes must be declared in scope (in both examples above, the prefix
               <code>app</code> must be bound to the namespace of the template, or of the function
               resp.)</p>
            <p>The request sequence (containing the <code>web:request</code> element and the request
               bodies) is passed to the XSLT function through its only parameter, to the named
               template through the template parameter named <code>web:input</code>, and to the
               stylesheet through the global parameter named <code>web:input</code> (the
               <code>web:request</code> element is also set as the context element for evaluating
               the stylesheet).</p>
            <p>The following is a simple example of a stylesheet, returning the XML representation
               of the HTTP request as the response itself:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;xsl:stylesheet xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform"
                xmlns:pkg="http://expath.org/ns/pkg"
                xmlns:web="http://expath.org/ns/webapp"
                exclude-result-prefixes="#all"
                version="2.0">

   &lt;pkg:import-uri>http://example.org/ns/my-webapp/echo.xsl&lt;/pkg:import-uri>

   &lt;xsl:template match="/">
      &lt;web:response status="200" message="Ok">
         &lt;web:body content-type="application/xml"/>
      &lt;/web:response>
      &lt;xsl:sequence select="."/>
   &lt;/xsl:template>

&lt;/xsl:stylesheet>
</eg>
         </div2>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="webapps">
         <head>Webapps</head>
         <p>An application (sometimes refered to as a webapp) is described by the webapp descriptor,
            and is composed of servlets, resources and filters, which can be grouped together,
            declares error handlers, and provides access to some configuration. An application is
            deployed within a web container, and has a dedicated context root.</p>
         <div2 id="context-root">
            <head>Context root</head>
            <p>When deployed into a web container, a webapp is assigned a context root. A context
               root is an absolute URL, which is the root of all URLs served by the webapp. That is,
               all URLs served by the webapp start with the same substring: the context root. For
               instance, if a webapp is deployed at <code>http://example.org/myapp/</code>, that
               means that all URLs starting with the same string will be dispatched by the container
               to that webapp, for instance:</p>
            <ulist>
               <item><p><code>http://example.org/myapp/</code></p></item>
               <item><p><code>http://example.org/myapp/index.html</code></p></item>
               <item><p><code>http://example.org/myapp/catalog/item/XYZ123</code></p></item>
               <item><p><code>http://example.org/myapp/catalog/item/XYZ123/buy</code></p></item>
               <item><p><code>http://example.org/myapp/search?q=brussels%20hotels</code></p></item>
            </ulist>
            <p>Until deployed, a webapp has no context root. All URLs defined within the webapp are
               either relative, or absolute (starting with "<code>/</code>"). When absolute, they
               are relative to the context root. For instance, a webapp handling the above URLs will
               define how to serve the following URLs:</p>
            <ulist>
               <item><p><code>/</code></p></item>
               <item><p><code>/index.html</code></p></item>
               <item><p><code>/catalog/item/XYZ123</code></p></item>
               <item><p><code>/catalog/item/XYZ123/buy</code></p></item>
               <item><p><code>/search?q=brussels%20hotels</code></p></item>
            </ulist>
            <p>If this webapp is deployed at the above context root, it will then serve the defined
               URLs. But it can also be deployed on localhost, for instance for test or dev
               purposes. The set of URLs served by the webapp will be different then, but the set of
               URLs served, when they are relative to the context root, are the same for a same
               webapp.</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="servlets">
            <head>Servlets</head>
            <p>A servlet is the association of a URL pattern to a component. A servlet can be given
               a name as well, for documentation and error reporting purposes. A servlet is
               configured in the webapp descriptor like the following:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;servlet name = NCName?
         filters = NCNames?>
   <emph>component</emph>,
   url
&lt;/servlet>

&lt;url pattern = string>
   match*
&lt;/url>

&lt;match group = integer
       name = NCName>
   <emph>empty</emph>
&lt;/match>
</eg>
            <p>The attribute <code>name</code> is the optional name of the servlet. The attribute
               <code>filters</code> is a space-separated list of filters, error handlers and/or
               chains. See the following sections for more information on those objects. The order
               of those names is important, as the objects are composed from the left-hand side (the
               top-most object) to the right-hand side (the bottom-most object, directly around the
               servlet). The pseudo element <emph><code>component</code></emph> is any of the
               existing component types defined in <specref ref="components"/>, that is either
               <code>xproc</code>, <code>xquery</code> or <code>xslt</code> (any of their variants).
               The attribute <code>pattern</code> must be a valid XML Schema regular expression (see
               <bibref ref="schema10-2"/>), matching a string starting with "<code>/</code>".</p>
            <p>When a HTTP request hits the web container, it identifies the webapp to serve the
               request (depending on their context roots; that mechanism is implementation-defined).
               Then it tries to match the request URL against all URL patterns in the webapp
               descriptor, is sequence in the document order, and picks the first servlet with a URL
               pattern matching the request URL. The corresponding component is executed, by passing
               the request sequence, and the result of the servlet is used to return a response to
               the client.</p>
            <p>The elements <code>match</code> of the matching URL are linked to the regex groups in
               the URL pattern. Because the URL pattern is a regex, matching against it can assign
               values to groups (by using parenthesis in the regex). The element <code>match</code>
               assigns a symbolic name to a group number. The corresponding values are put into the
               <code>web:request</code> element, more precisely in its child element
               <code>web:path</code>. For example the following servlet definition, associating an
               XSLT stylesheet component to a URL pattern, and naming some specific parts of the
               URL:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;servlet name="user">
   &lt;xslt uri="http://example.org/myapp/users.xsl"/>
   &lt;url pattern="/users/([a-z0-9]+)">
      &lt;match group="1" name="id"/>
   &lt;/url>
&lt;/servlet></eg>
            <p>will produce the following <code>path</code> element when matching a URL ending with
               <code>/users/fgeorges</code>:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;path>
   &lt;part>/users/&lt;/part>
   &lt;match name="id">fgeorges&lt;/match>
&lt;/path></eg>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="resources">
            <head>Resources</head>
            <p>A resource is a special type of servlet, defined by the following element:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;resource pattern = string
          rewrite = string?
          media-type = string>
   <emph>empty</emph>
&lt;/resource></eg>
            <p>The <code>pattern</code> attribute has the same meaning as for <code>servlet</code>.
               A resource is a servlet, so when the URL dispatcher looks sequentially through the
               URL patterns for a match, that includes resources as well. If a resource matches the
               URL and has a <code>rewrite</code> attribute, this one is interpreted as a regex
               replacement string, and the path used to be resolved is the result of evaluating the
               following expression, where <code>$url</code> is the actual URL being matched:
               <code>replace($url,@pattern,@rewrite)</code>.</p>
            <p>The resulting path (either the resolved URL or the replaced string if their is a
               <code>rewrite</code> attribute) is then resolved into the application package. If the
               path starts with a slash, this one removed, then the path is resolved against the
               webapp package content directory. The resulting file is the body of the response, the
               value of the <code>media-type</code> attribute is the value of the response header
               Content-Type, and the response status is "<code>200 - OK</code>". If the file does
               not exists, the response status is "<code>400 - Not Found</code>" and the content of
               the response is implementation-defined.</p>
            <p>For instance, the following definitions set the correct Content-Type for CSS
               stylesheets and PNG images, which are resolve in the package in the sub-directories
               <code>style/</code> and <code>images/</code> respectively:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;resource pattern="/style/.+\.css"  media-type="text/css"/>
&lt;resource pattern="/images/.+\.png" media-type="image/png"/></eg>
            <p>The following example rewrite the URL so <code>/style/print</code> will resolve in
               the webapp package content dir as <code>css/main-print.css</code>:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;resource pattern="/style/(.+)" rewrite="css/main-$1.css" media-type="text/css"/></eg>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="filters">
            <head>Filters</head>
            <p>A filter has a name and two components, the "<emph>in</emph>" and the
               "<emph>out</emph>" component. Both components are optional, but at least one is
               required:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;filter name = NCName>
   in?,
   out?
&lt;/filter>

&lt;in>
   <emph>component</emph>
&lt;/in>

&lt;out>
   <emph>component</emph>
&lt;/out></eg>
            <p>When a filter is attached to a servlet, the input sequence flowing to the servlet
               first passes to the filter "<emph>in</emph>" component if any. The input sequence
               becomes the input sequence of the "<emph>in</emph>" component, and the result of
               evaluating it becomes the input sequence of the servlet component. The result of
               evaluating the servlet component passes then through the filter "<emph>out</emph>"
               component, if any. The result of the servlet becomes the "<emph>out</emph>" component
               input sequence, and the result of evaluating it becomes the result returned to the
               container.</p>
            <p>There are several ways to set a filter around a servlet. Actually, filters can be
               chained and mixed with error handlers, so a filter can be set around either a
               component, a filter, or an error handler. The concept remains the same, the
               <emph>in</emph> and <emph>out</emph> components are executed before and after the
               wrapped object.</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="error-handling">
            <head>Error handling</head>
            <p>Error handlers are a special sort of filter. The do not have any <emph>in</emph> nor
               <emph>out</emph> component, so they are like pass-through with regards of the inputs
               and outputs. However, if an error is thrown in the wrapped object, it offers a way to
               catch it and so to compute an alternative result sequence. This implementation of an
               error handler is a user-provided component, which is passed several information about
               the error (the user has the opportunity to pass all sort of data to
               <code>fn:error()</code> in XSLT and XQuery, and to <code>p:error</code> in XProc, so
               a real customized error reporting and handling strategy can be set up). An error
               handler is defined by using the following element:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;error name = NCName
       catch = CatchErrorList>
   <emph>component</emph>
&lt;/error></eg>
            <p>As any filter, an error handler has a name, which is an NCName. It has also a catch
               error list, the format of which is defined by the production rule
               <code>CatchErrorList</code> in <bibref ref="xquery30"/>. The catch error list is a
               '|'-separated list of QName wildcards, that is where you can substitute either the
               prefix, the local name or the whole name by a '*' (meaning "any value here"). In
               addition it allows using EQNames for explicitly setting the namespace URI in the
               expression, without having to bind it to a prefix. Such a list therefore identifies a
               set of matching QNames. When an error is thrown by a component and go up the stack
               through the error handler, it is caught is its code matches the catch error list. In
               that case the error is caught, the component is executed, and its result becomes the
               result sequence of the error handler.</p>
            <p>Some examples of catch error lists, given the corresponding prefixes are bound
               in-scope:</p>
            <ulist>
               <item>
                  <p>"<code>app:XYZ001</code>": catch a specific error</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>"<code>*</code>": catch all errors</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>"<code>app:*</code>": catch all errors in the namespace bound to the prefix
                     "app"</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>"<code>app:ABC067|app:XYZ001</code>": catch both errors, explicitly</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>"<code>app:*|lib:*|err:XYZ001</code>": catch all errors in the namespace bound
                     to the prefix "app", and all the errors in the namespace bound to the prefix
                     "lib", and the error with the QName "err:XYZ001"</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>"<code>'http://example.org/ns/error':XYZ001</code>": catch the error with local
                     name "XYZ001" in the namespace "http://example.org/ns/error"</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>"<code>'http://example.org/ns/error':*</code>": catch all errors in the
                     namespace "http://example.org/ns/error"</p>
               </item>
            </ulist>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="chains">
            <head>Chains</head>
            <p>A chain is a special type of filter, composing other filters. It is defined using the
               following element:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;chain name = NCName
       filters = NCNames?>
   (chain
    |error
    |filter)*
&lt;/chain>

&lt;chain ref = NCName>
   <emph>empty</emph>
&lt;/chain>

&lt;error ref = NCName>
   <emph>empty</emph>
&lt;/error>

&lt;error catch = CatchErrorList>
   <emph>component</emph>
&lt;/error>

&lt;filter ref = NCName>
   <emph>empty</emph>
&lt;/filter>

&lt;filter>
   in?,
   out?
&lt;/filter></eg>
            <p>The elements <code>error</code> and <code>filter</code>, when inside a chain, are
               either empty references to a global named error handler or filter, or are the
               anoymous equivalent of their global representation (same format, without the
               attribute <code>name</code>). The element <code>chain</code>, when appearing as a
               child, must be a reference to a named chain (so one can compose chains). If the
               attribute <code>filters</code> is not present, there must be at least one child
               element. If the attribute <code>filters</code> is present, the <code>chain</code>
               element must be empty. This attribute is a shortcut to set a chain by using only
               named filters, and is constructed like with the attribute <code>filters</code> on the
               element <code>servlet</code> (left-hand name is the top-most filter).</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="groups">
            <head>Groups</head>
            <p>Groups are a way to set the same filters to a group of servlets. A group is a lexical
               wrapper around several servlet definitions:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;group filters = NCNames?>
   (group
    |servlet)+
&lt;/group></eg>
            <p>As we see, groups can be nested. They have a filter chain (using the same attribute
               <code>filters</code> as the element <code>servlet</code>), and contain servlets and
               other groups. The only effect is to add their filter chain to each object they
               contain. Their filters are added right before the object own filters (so after any
               application filter chain, and after any parent group filter chain).</p>
            <p>For instance, in the following example:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;group filters="first second">
   &lt;servlet name="un" filters="third fourth">
      ...
   &lt;/servlet>
   &lt;group filters="fifth">
      &lt;servlet name="deux">
         ...
      &lt;/servlet>
      &lt;servlet name="trois" filters="sixth">
         ...
      &lt;/servlet>
   &lt;/servlet>
&lt;/group></eg>
            <p>the servlet "un" is wrapped by the filter chain "first second third fourth" (in that
               order), "deux" is wrapped by "first second fifth", and "trois" by "first second fifth
               sixth".</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="config">
            <head>Config</head>
            <p>The following functions provide access to configuration parameters and documents. The
               webapp author can define any parameter and document he/she needs, and access them by
               name.</p>
            <eg>
<ex:function>web:config-param</ex:function>($name as <ex:type>xs:string</ex:type>) as <ex:type>xs:string?</ex:type>
<ex:function>web:config-param</ex:function>($name as <ex:type>xs:string</ex:type>,
                 $default as <ex:type>xs:string</ex:type>?) as <ex:type>xs:string</ex:type>?
<ex:function>web:config-doc</ex:function>($name as <ex:type>xs:string</ex:type>) as <ex:type>document-node()?</ex:type>
</eg>
            <p>Depending on the webapp specific needs, the easiest way to define configuration
               information might be using string parameters, or using documents. In either case, the
               config is accessible in read-only. This mechanism is not replacing a database. The
               way the config parameters and documents are provided is implementation-defined.</p>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="applications">
            <head>Applications</head>
            <p>The application as a whole is represented using the following element:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;application filters = NCNames?>
   <emph>empty</emph>
&lt;/application>
</eg>
            <p>This element provides a convenient way to set filters to all servlets and resources
               within the application (like an error-handler, a view layer, or an authentication
               filter).</p>
         </div2>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="descriptor">
         <head>Webapp descriptor</head>
         <p>This section defines the webapp descriptor <code>expath-web.xml</code>. Only the overall
            structure of the descriptor is given, referencing to elements defined in the previous
            section, <specref ref="webapps"/>. See the section <specref ref="expath-pkg.xsd"/> for a
            formal schema of the entire descriptor format.</p>
         <p>The root element of the descriptor is <code>webapp</code>:</p>
         <eg>
&lt;webapp name = uri
        abbrev = NCName
        version = string
        spec = string>
   title,
   home?,
   (application
    |chain
    |error
    |filter
    |group
    |resource
    |servlet)+
&lt;/webapp>

&lt;title>
   <emph>string</emph>
&lt;/title>

&lt;home>
   <emph>uri</emph>
&lt;/home>
</eg>
         <p>A webapp is identified by a name, an abbrev and a version number (all three following
            the same rules as their corresponding attributes in <bibref ref="pkg"/>). The attribute
            <code>spec</code> is the version of the packaging specification the package conforms to.
            The current specification requires the package to use the spec number <code>1.0</code>
            (no forward compatibility rules are defined, a processor conforming to this
            specification has to generate an error if the spec number is different than the string
            <code>1.0</code>). The title is a plain string, and the home is a URL pointing to the
            webapp's or project's homepage or website. The rest of the webapp element is composed of
            any combination of the elements <code>application</code>, <code>error</code>,
            <code>filter</code>, <code>group</code> and <code>servlet</code>.</p>
         <p>The following is an example of a descriptor, for a simple webapp with 2 components: an
            XProc pipeline and an XQuery query, resp. bound to the URLs patterns <code>/home</code>
            and <code>/users/([a-z0-9]+)</code>, as well as a filter on the second one and an error
            handler for the entire application (it also defines a few resource patterns):</p>
         <eg>
&lt;webapp xmlns="http://expath.org/ns/webapp/descriptor"
        xmlns:app="http://example.org/ns/someapp"
        name="http://example.org/someapp"
        abbrev="someapp"
        version="2.6.0">

   &lt;title>Example website&lt;/title>

   &lt;resource pattern="/style/.+\.css"  media-type="text/css"/>
   &lt;resource pattern="/images/.+\.png" media-type="image/png"/>

   &lt;application filters="errors"/>

   &lt;filter name="authenticate">
      &lt;in>
         &lt;xslt uri="http://example.org/someapp/authenticate.xsl"/>
      &lt;/in>
   &lt;/filter>

   &lt;error name="errors" catch="*">
      &lt;xproc uri="http://example.org/someapp/errors.xproc"/>
   &lt;/error>

   &lt;!-- The homepage. -->
   &lt;servlet name="home">
      &lt;xproc uri="http://example.org/someapp/home.xproc"/>
      &lt;url pattern="/home"/>
   &lt;/servlet>

   &lt;!-- The users. The user ID in the URL is set to the param "user". -->
   &lt;servlet name="users" filters="authenticate">
      &lt;xquery uri="http://example.org/someapp/users.xq"/>
      &lt;url pattern="/users/([a-z0-9]+)">
         &lt;match group="1" name="user"/>
      &lt;/url>
   &lt;/servlet>

&lt;/webapp>
</eg>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="packaging">
         <head>Packaging</head>
         <p>A webapp is packaged using <bibref ref="pkg"/>. It is therefore a regular package and
            can benefit from all the tools supporting this specification. In addition to the
            standard package format, a webapp contain the webapp descriptor in a file called
            <code>expath-web.xml</code>, at the root of the package.</p>
         <p>For instance, the above descriptor example could define a webapp packaged like the
            following:</p>
         <eg>
expath-pkg.xml
expath-web.xml
content/
   filters/
      auth.xsl
      errors.xproc
   images/
      logo.png
   servlets/
      home.xproc
      users.xq
   style/
      style.css
</eg>
         <p>Note that there the name of the files for the components do not necessarily match the
            last part of their public URI. The components (including the servlets and the components
            used in filters and error handlers) must be declared in the package descriptor, that is
            <code>expath-pkg.xml</code>.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="functions">
         <head>Webapp functions</head>
         <p>Those functions are defined in the namespace <code>web</code>.</p>
         <div2 id="fields">
            <head>Fields</head>
            <p>A webapp can access and store values, attached to different contexts: the container,
               the webapp, the session, and the request. The request is the current HTTP request
               being served, the session is the session of the request, the webapp is the one
               containing the component serving the request, and the container represents the webapp
               container as a whole.</p>
            <p>A field has a name (a string) and a value (any sequence). The names beginning with
               "web:" are reserved for this specification. Note that "web:" is not a namespace
               prefix, and then does not need to be bound by any mean, field names are simple
               strings.</p>
            <p>Each set of fields has three corresponding functions: one to get the value of a field
               given its name, one to set its value, and one to enumerate the names of all existing
               fields.</p>
            <p>For the request fields:</p>
            <eg>
<ex:function>web:get-request-field</ex:function>($name as <ex:type>xs:string</ex:type>) as <ex:type>item()*</ex:type>
<ex:function>web:set-request-field</ex:function>($name as <ex:type>xs:string</ex:type>,
                      $value as <ex:type>item()*</ex:type>) as <ex:type>empty-sequence()</ex:type>
<ex:function>web:get-request-field-names</ex:function>() as <ex:type>xs:string*</ex:type>
</eg>
            <p>For the session fields:</p>
            <eg>
<ex:function>web:get-session-field</ex:function>($name as <ex:type>xs:string</ex:type>) as <ex:type>item()*</ex:type>
<ex:function>web:set-session-field</ex:function>($name as <ex:type>xs:string</ex:type>,
                      $value as <ex:type>item()*</ex:type>) as <ex:type>empty-sequence()</ex:type>
<ex:function>web:get-session-field-names</ex:function>() as <ex:type>xs:string*</ex:type>
</eg>
            <p>For the webapp fields:</p>
            <eg>
<ex:function>web:get-webapp-field</ex:function>($name as <ex:type>xs:string</ex:type>) as <ex:type>item()*</ex:type>
<ex:function>web:set-webapp-field</ex:function>($name as <ex:type>xs:string</ex:type>,
                     $value as <ex:type>item()*</ex:type>) as <ex:type>empty-sequence()</ex:type>
<ex:function>web:get-webapp-field-names</ex:function>() as <ex:type>xs:string*</ex:type>
</eg>
            <p>For the container fields:</p>
            <eg>
<ex:function>web:get-container-field</ex:function>($name as <ex:type>xs:string</ex:type>) as <ex:type>item()*</ex:type>
<ex:function>web:set-container-field</ex:function>($name as <ex:type>xs:string</ex:type>,
                        $value as <ex:type>item()*</ex:type>) as <ex:type>empty-sequence()</ex:type>
<ex:function>web:get-container-field-names</ex:function>() as <ex:type>xs:string*</ex:type>
</eg>
            <p>The request contains the following field:</p>
            <ulist>
               <item>
                  <p><code>web:request-id</code>: a string identifying uniquely the request being
                     treated. The string macthes the regex "[-_a-zA-Z0-9]+" and is therefore safe to
                     use in a file name. The strings are ordered through time, that is comparing two
                     request IDs using the code point collation must order them occordingly to the
                     time they were received by the server. The precision is implementation-defined
                     (that is, an implementation might say that the order between 2 request IDs for
                     2 requests received within the same second is undefined).</p>
               </item>
            </ulist>
            <p>The container contains the following fields:</p>
            <ulist>
               <item>
                  <p><code>web:product</code>: the implementation (usually a product name and a
                     version number).</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p><code>web:product-html</code>: a HTML formatted version of the property
                     <code>web:product</code>. The HTML must be valid HTML to be the content of a
                     <code>p</code> or a <code>div</code> element (usually it is the same as
                     <code>web:product</code>, with additional hyperlinks).</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p><code>web:vendor</code>: the vendor of the product (usually a person, a company
                     or an open-source group).</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p><code>web:vendor-html</code>: a HTML formatted version of the property
                     <code>web:vendor</code>. The HTML must be valid HTML to be the content of a
                     <code>p</code> or a <code>div</code> element (usually it is the same as
                     <code>web:vendor</code>, with additional hyperlinks).</p>
               </item>
            </ulist>
         </div2>
         <div2 id="parse">
            <head>Parse HTTP</head>
            <eg>
<ex:function>web:parse-header-value</ex:function>($header as <ex:type>xs:string</ex:type>) as <ex:type>element(web:header)</ex:type>
</eg>
            <p>This function parses the value of a structured HTTP header. It returns it in the form
               of the following element:</p>
            <p>Some HTTP headers have values that can be decomposed into multiple elements. In order
               to be processed by this function, such headers must be in the following form:</p>
            <eg>
 header  = [ element ] *( "," [ element ] )
 element = name [ "=" [ value ] ] *( ";" [ param ] )
 param   = name [ "=" [ value ] ]

 name    = token
 value   = ( token | quoted-string )

 token         = 1*&lt;any char except "=", ",", ";", &lt;"> and
                       white space>
 quoted-string = &lt;"> *( text | quoted-char ) &lt;">
 text          = any char except &lt;">
 quoted-char   = "\" char
</eg>
            <p>Any amount of white space is allowed between any part of the header, element or param
               and is ignored. The function returns the following format, representing elements and
               params with an XML format. A missing value in any element or param will be returned
               as an empty attribute <code>value</code>; if the "=" is also missing, the attribute
               <code>value</code> is not generated at all.</p>
            <eg>
&lt;header>
   element+
&lt;/header>

&lt;element name = string>
   param*
&lt;/element>

&lt;param name = string
       value = string>
   <emph>empty</emph>
&lt;/param>
</eg>
            <p>For example, the following call:</p>
            <eg>
web:parse-header-value('text/html,application/xhtml+xml,application/xml;q=0.9,*/*;q=0.8')
</eg>
            <p>returns the following element:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;header>
   &lt;element name="text/html"/>
   &lt;element name="application/xhtml+xml"/>
   &lt;element name="application/xml">
      &lt;param name="q" value="0.9"/>
   &lt;/element>
   &lt;element name="*/*">
      &lt;param name="q" value="0.8"/>
   &lt;/element>
&lt;/header>
</eg>
            <p>The user can then easily access the several elements (here the different MIME types),
               as well as their parameters (here their optional relative quality factors).</p>
            <eg>
<ex:function>web:parse-basic-auth</ex:function>($header as <ex:type>xs:string</ex:type>) as <ex:type>element(web:basic-auth)</ex:type>
</eg>
            <p>This function parses the value of a Basic Access Authentication header, as defined in
               <bibref ref="rfc2617"/>. It returns it in the form of the following element:</p>
            <eg>
&lt;basic-auth username = string
            password = string>
   <emph>empty</emph>
&lt;/basic-auth>
</eg>
            <p>The value of the header is "Basic abc" where <code>abc</code> is "user:password"
               encoded using base64.</p>
         </div2>
      </div1>
   </body>
   <back>
      <div1 id="expath-pkg.xsd">
         <head>Webapp schema</head>
         <eg><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="schema/webapp.xsd" parse="text"/></eg>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="references">
         <head>References</head>
         <blist>
            <bibl id="pkg" key="EXPath Packaging System"><loc href="http://expath.org/spec/pkg"
               >Packaging System</loc>. Florent Georges, editor. EXPath. 9 May 2012.</bibl>
            <bibl id="rfc2616" key="RFC 2616"><loc href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2616.txt">RFC
               2616: Hypertext Transfer Protocol -- HTTP/1.1</loc>. R. Fielding, J. Gettys, J.
               Mogul, H. Frystyk, L. Masinter, P. Leach and T. Berners-Lee, editors. Internet
               Engineering Task Force. June, 1999.</bibl>
            <bibl id="rfc2617" key="RFC 2617"><loc href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2617.txt">RFC
               2617: HTTP Authentication: Basic and Digest Access Authentication</loc>. J. Franks,
               P. Hallam-Baker, J. Hostetler, S. Lawrence, P. Leach, A. Luotonen and L. Stewart,
               editors. Internet Engineering Task Force. June, 1999.</bibl>
            <bibl id="rfc3023" key="RFC 3023"><loc href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3023.txt">RFC
               3023: XML Media Types</loc>. M. Murata, S. St. Laurent and D. Kohn, editors.
               Internet Engineering Task Force. January, 2001.</bibl>
            <bibl id="schema10-2" key="XML Schema Datatypes"><loc
               href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2/">XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes Second
               Edition</loc>. P. Viron and A. Malhotra, editors. W3C. October, 2013.</bibl>
            <bibl id="xquery30" key="XQuery 3.0"><loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xquery-30/">XQuery
               3.0: An XML Query Language</loc>. J. Robie, D. Chamberlin, M. Dyck and J. Snelson,
               editors. W3C. XXX, 2013. (TODO: Update the publication date once XQuery 3.0 has been
               published)</bibl>
         </blist>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="todo">
         <head>TODO list</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Definition: define the name <kw>accessor</kw>, to use when I use "URL" as "URL
                  relatively to the context root", for instance for matching against patterns. And
                  use it consistently across the spec.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Definition: define the format of the several <kw>names</kw> (servlets, url
                  matches, filters, chains, error handlers, etc.) And use it consistently across the
                  spec. Or do we just use NCName all the time?</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The <kw>filters</kw> mechanism is not satisfactory. It does not allow a filter to
                  decide whether or not (and when) the wrapped component is called. The minimal use
                  case to accomodate is an authentication filter returning a "401 Unauthorized" when
                  the user is not connected, without actually calling the wrapped component at all).
                  An idea could be to shortcut the component if the filter returns a valid response
                  sequence (starting with an element <code>web:response</code>...)</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The <kw>config</kw> mechanism is probably under-specified. We should probably
                  define how a webapp provides default values (where in the package), as well as how
                  this is represented in an on-disk repository (this is optional, but this is a way
                  to align several impementations if they choose the same kind of approach).</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>In addition to <code>web:parse-basic-auth()</code>, add a function to support
                  <kw>Digest</kw> Access Authentication (see <bibref ref="rfc2617"/>).</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div1>
   </back>
</spec>
