<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/06/schema/xmlspec.rng" type="xml"?>

<spec role="editors-copy">
   <header>
      <title>Packaging System</title>
      <w3c-designation>w3c-designation</w3c-designation>
      <w3c-doctype>EXPath Candidate Module</w3c-doctype>
      <pubdate>
         <day>1</day>
         <month>September</month>
         <year>2009</year>
      </pubdate>
      <publoc>
         <loc href="http://expath.org/spec/pkg/20090901"/>
      </publoc>
      <altlocs>
         <loc href="http://expath.org/spec/pkg/20090901.xml">XML</loc>
      </altlocs>
      <latestloc>
         <loc href="http://expath.org/spec/pkg"/>
      </latestloc>
      <!--prevlocs>
         <loc href="http://expath.org/spec/pkg/2009mmdd"/>
         <loc href="http://expath.org/spec/pkg/2009mmdd"/>
         ...
      </prevlocs-->
      <authlist>
         <author>
            <name>Florent Georges</name>
            <affiliation>H²O Consulting</affiliation>
         </author>
      </authlist>
      <copyright>
         <p/>
      </copyright>
      <abstract>
         <p>This proposal defines a packaging system for various core XML technologies: XSLT,
            XQuery, and XProc. The goal is to define it in a way enough generic so to adapt it to
            other technologies in the future (such as XML Schema, XForms, etc.) using the same
            framework. Besides enabling the delivery of libraries written in standard XSLT, XQuery
            and XProc, it provides support for extensions specific to some processors, as well as
            enabling new processors to be supported by using the same framework.</p>
      </abstract>
      <status>
         <p>Must be ignored, but is required by the schema...</p>
      </status>
      <langusage>
         <language>langusage</language>
      </langusage>
      <revisiondesc>
         <p>revisiondesc</p>
      </revisiondesc>
   </header>
   <body>
      <div1>
         <head>Introduction</head>
         <p>XSLT, XQuery and XProc are amazing programming languages. But they lack a large choice
            of libraries, and when such libraries do exist, this is a challenge to install. There is
            no automatic install process, the rules are different for each processor, library
            authors do not follow the same rules regarding the info they provide, the cataloging,
            the way they reference third-party libraries, etc.</p>
         <p>All those problems (well, most of them) can be addressed by a packaging system that
            would be broadly adopted by processor vendors and library authors. The cornerstone of
            such a system is the packaging format: a description of the information to be provided
            by the library authors and how to provide and structure them.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1>
         <head>Editorial notes</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Should the package system define a set of XPath functions? Instead of just
                  defining the package format and letting everything else as implementation-defined,
                  should it in addition define a module of functions to install, delete, and more
                  generally manage packages from within a processor?</p>
               <p>Drawback: potential problems if the processor requires to be stopped?</p>
               <p>Advantages: enables writing tools on top of the system (one single graphical
                  package manager for one system, simply using the XPath functions, as well as easy
                  integration within IDEs; or even other systems could be more easily be built on
                  top of it, like a packaging system for XRX applications for instance.)</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Should it be possible to have two different kinds of files with the same public
                  URI? Put another way, should we have a different URI space for each kind of files?
                  I think this would be necessary for instance to enable deploying a package with
                  both an XML schema and an XQuery library module with the same target namespace. I
                  am not sure this is a best practice, but I am sure that will lead to at least one
                  company's standard practices...</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div1>
      <div1>
         <head>Concepts</head>
         <p>A library is a set of files fulfilling a common purpose. An XSLT library can for
            instance provide a set of template rules and functions to help formating a particular
            XML document type. A package is a way to bundle those files into a single ZIP file,
            following a defined structure and providing more information within the <emph>package
               descriptor</emph>. The package descriptor is a plain XML file, named
               <code>expath-pkg.xml</code> at the root of the ZIP file, and containing information
            about the library (like its name and its version number) and about the files it provides
            and how to reference them (for instance stylesheets and query modules.)</p>
         <p>The ZIP file structure (aka the package structure) must have exactly two entries at the
            top-level (aka the root): the package descriptor and one directory entry. This directory
            contains all the library files, and all file references in the package descriptor are
            relative to this directory. This directory is called the <emph>library
            directory</emph>.</p>
         <p>All the elements in the package descriptor are defined in the namespace
               <code>http://expath.org/mod/expath-pkg</code>. All the elements defined in this
            specification or used in samples and in text are in this namespace, even if no prefix is
            used. The root element is <code>package</code>, and contains exactly one child element
               <code>module</code>:</p>
         <eg>
&lt;package>
   module
&lt;/package>

&lt;module name = NCName
        version = string>
   title,
   (xsl
   |xquery
   |xproc
   |xsd
   |rng
   |rnc
   |...)+
&lt;/module></eg>
         <p><code>name</code> is the library name. The top-level directory in the package structure
            must have the exact same name. The module has also a version number, and a
            human-readable title. It then provides information about one or several files. In
            addition to those standard file descriptors, it can also contain elements specific to
            some processors (for instance an element for Saxon, eXist, etc.) Details are provided
            below.</p>
         <p>The files configured in the module are the files <emph>exported</emph> by the module.
            But the whole library directory must be preserved. Indeed, it can contain other, private
            files, aimed to be used only from within library files, not from the outside.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1>
         <head>Standard X* files</head>
         <p>Here is the description of the standard file kinds supported by this specification, and
            how they contribute to the package descriptor document type.</p>
         <div2>
            <head>XSLT</head>
            <p>An XSLT file is associated a <emph>public import URI</emph>. This URI must be an
               absolute URI (most often a URN or an HTTP URI.) This is the URI to use in an XSLT
               import instruction (aka <code>xsl:import</code>) to import the XSLT file provided in
               the package. This file is configured with the element <code>xsl</code>.</p>
            <eg>
&lt;xsl>
   import-uri,
   file
&lt;/xsl></eg>
            <p>The element <code>file</code> contains the path to the file within the package
               structure, relative to the library directory. Both elements <code>import-uri</code>
               and <code>file</code> are of type <code>anyURI</code>.</p>
         </div2>
         <div2>
            <head>XQuery</head>
            <p>An XQuery library module is referenced by its namespace URI. Thus the
                  <code>xquery</code> element associates a namespace URI to an XQuery file. An
               importing module just need to use an import statement of the form <code>import module
                  namespace xx = "&lt;namespace-uri>";</code>.</p>
            <eg>
&lt;xquery>
   namespace,
   file
&lt;/xquery></eg>
            <p>Note that there is no way to set any location hint (as the <code>at</code> clause in
               the import statement.) To use this packaging system, an XQuery library module must be
               referenced by its target namespace.</p>
         </div2>
         <div2>
            <head>XProc</head>
            <p>An XProc pipeline, like an XSLT stylesheet, is associated a <emph>public import
                  URI</emph>, aimed to be used in an XProc <code>p:import</code> statement.</p>
            <eg>
&lt;xproc>
   import-uri,
   file
&lt;/xproc></eg>
         </div2>
         <div2>
            <head>XML Schema</head>
            <p>An XML schema can be imported using its target namespace. Like for XQuery, there is
               no way to use any <code>schemaLocation</code> instead. There is neither the ability
               to set several files as several sources for the schema. If the schema is spread over
               multiple files, there must be one top-level file that includes the other files.</p>
            <eg>
&lt;xsd>
   namespace,
   file
&lt;/xsd></eg>
            <p>(TODO: Should we support schemas with empty target namespace? I am sure this is a
               good idea in a packaging system...)</p>
         </div2>
         <div2>
            <head>RelaxNG</head>
            <p>A RelaxNG schema, like an XSLT stylesheet, is associated a public import URI, aimed
               to be used in an <emph>import</emph> statement (either the <emph>include</emph>
               element for an RNG schema or an <emph>import</emph> directive for an RNC schema.)</p>
            <eg>
&lt;rng>
   import-uri,
   file
&lt;/rng>

&lt;rnc>
   import-uri,
   file
&lt;/xrnc></eg>
         </div2>
         <div2>
            <head>Schematron</head>
            <p>A Schematron schema is associated a public URI.</p>
            <eg>
&lt;schematron>
   import-uri,
   file
&lt;/schematron></eg>
         </div2>
         <div2>
            <head>NVDL</head>
            <p>An NVDL script is associated a public URI.</p>
            <eg>
&lt;nvdl>
   import-uri,
   file
&lt;/nvdl></eg>
         </div2>
         <div2>
            <head>Not supported file kinds</head>
            <p>Documentation (like result of XSLStyle or xqDoc) is not taken into account in the
               packaging format, though that could be used by IDEs for instance to provide
               documentation for functions in an editor with a live completion feature. Some support
               for documentation can of course be added as a product-specific feature to the package
               descriptor.</p>
         </div2>
         <div2>
            <head>Package example</head>
            <p>... [ package structure + package descriptor ] ...</p>
         </div2>
      </div1>
      <div1>
         <head>Processor-specific files</head>
         <p>Bla-bla...</p>
         <div2>
            <head>Saxon</head>
            <p>Bla-bla...</p>
            <p>... classes for <loc
                  href="http://www.saxonica.com/documentation/extensibility/functions.html"
                  >extension functions</loc> (both Java and .Net?), classes for <loc
                  href="http://www.saxonica.com/documentation/extensibility/instructions.html"
                  >extension instructions</loc>, classes for <loc
                  href="http://www.saxonica.com/documentation/extensibility/localizing.html"
                  >localizing numbers and dates</loc>, URI resolvers, etc.</p>
         </div2>
         <div2>
            <head>Xalan</head>
            <p>Bla-bla...</p>
         </div2>
         <div2>
            <head>eXist</head>
            <p>Bla-bla...</p>
         </div2>
         <div2>
            <head>MarkLogic</head>
            <p>Bla-bla...</p>
         </div2>
         <div2>
            <head>Zorba</head>
            <p>Bla-bla...</p>
         </div2>
         <div2>
            <head>Calabash</head>
            <p>Bla-bla...</p>
         </div2>
         <div2>
            <head>Calumet</head>
            <p>Bla-bla...</p>
         </div2>
         <div2>
            <head>xmlsh</head>
            <p>Bla-bla...</p>
         </div2>
      </div1>
      <div1>
         <head>Extensibility</head>
         <p>Bla-bla...</p>
      </div1>
   </body>
   <back>
      <div1>
         <head>Package descriptor schema</head>
         <eg><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../xsd/expath-pkg.xsd" parse="text"/></eg>
         <p>(or RNC?)</p>
      </div1>
      <div1>
         <head>References</head>
         <blist>
            <bibl id="for-ref" key="To Display">An <loc href="http://www.example.com/">example
                  reference</loc>. Example &amp; Co.</bibl>
         </blist>
      </div1>
   </back>
</spec>
